<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch02-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

<para>The gimli Git server provides repositories for all of the *LFS
projects (and some others). The repository which we are interested in for
LFS editing is (unsurprisingly) the LFS repository. A complete list of the
modules which are available can be found using the Trac source browser
interface at
<ulink url="http://wiki.linuxfromscratch.org/lfs/browser"/>.</para> 

<para>There are two types of Git access provided to the LFS tree.
Firstly, there is anonymous read-only access which anyone can use.
Secondly, there is read-write access granted to active editors who have
accounts on gimli.</para>

<note>
  <title>Note to Subversion Users</title>
  <para>
    Subversion is a centralized version control system, which means there
    is a unique repository on the server, and that users can 
    <emphasis>check out</emphasis> that repository to a working directory
    on their local machine. Users with write access can then
    <emphasis>commit</emphasis> their modifications to the repository
    on the server.
  </para>
  <para>
    Git is a distributed version control system, which means that all users
    have their own repository. The repository on the server is nothing more
    than the others, except that a public access is granted to it. The action
    of copying the repository from the server to the local machine is named
    <emphasis>cloning</emphasis>. Checking out and committing thus only occur
    locally. The action of synchronizing the public repository with the
    local one is named <emphasis>pull</emphasis> (public to local) or
    <emphasis>push</emphasis> (local to public for users with write access).
  </para>
</note>
</sect1>
